<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reason regulate[d], or, Brief reflections upon a l[ate] treatise of human-reason by T.P.</title>
            <author>T. P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54036</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25516</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09003820</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09003820</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42188</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54036)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42188)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1291:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reason regulate[d], or, Brief reflections upon a l[ate] treatise of human-reason by T.P.</title>
                  <author>T. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>74, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page cropped, missing letters supplied from caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith and reason.</term>
               <term>Rationalism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:42188:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THe Reader may pleaſe to take notice that theſe ſhort Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations were written within two months after the Publication of that Treatiſe of <hi>Human Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42188:1"/>
            <p>REASON REGULATED OR, Brief Reflections, upon a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> TREATISE of <hi>HVMAN-REASON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>T. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42188:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42188:2"/>
            <head>Reaſon Regulated: OR, Brief Reflections upon a late Treatiſe of <hi>Human-Reaſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE very ſame Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, which cauſed that Ingenious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to publiſh his HVMAN-REASON <hi>and his Search into the Nature, and Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Religion,</hi> (<hi>and thoſe were</hi> [he ſays] <hi>to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate it's Effects to others;</hi>) carri'd me alſo on, to a reſolution of expoſing theſe ſhort Obſervations, to the View of ſome of my Particular Friends; though. I muſt confeſs, the Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Quaintneſs, and Rarity (not to ſay Intricacy) of his Arguments, were enough (at firſt ſight) to deterr, and ſtartle a much ſtronger <hi>Humanist,</hi> than my ſelf, from oppoſing ſo great
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42188:3"/>a Maſter of <hi>Reaſon:</hi> Yet when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, that if (according to his own Principles) I follow'd ſincerely the Dictamen, or ſway, of my own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (for <hi>Human Reaſon</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe,) I could not, as to the Period or Effect, (which is to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at Truth, and Happineſs,) poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly err, or be miſguided, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently raiſe in him, the leaſt Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt me; This Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (I ſay) conquer'd all other Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles, and Arguments to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and encourag'd me to proſecute my Deſign: For (thought I) in this Procedure (if he dares believe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) my Reaſon (though directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) muſt perfectly agree with his. Now if this be Implicatory, and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd (which truly in my Judgement, is in a very high Degree); He that broach'd the Opinion muſt (if he can) either reconcile, or defend it.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42188:3"/>
            <p> FFirſt he ſays, <hi>That the Variety of Guides in ſo long, and dangerous a Journey;</hi> (meaning I ſuppoſe our Pilgrimage to Heaven) <hi>where he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times meets with no Tract, or Path at all, and ſometimes with ſo many, and thoſe ſo contrary in the Appearance of their First Entry; will confound him more than the want, and in this Intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Labyrinth, reſolves to follow his own private Reaſon, and Judgment:</hi> Which cannot Rationally diſprove me in affirming, 'Tis evident to moſt Mens <hi>Humane Reaſon,</hi> (upon a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and impartial ſearch) that the Directive part or Guides of Gods Church, are as diſcernable from all Pretenders to, and Uſurpers of that Office, as Light is from Darkneſs, or Day from Night; and therefore <hi>His Plea of Variety</hi> (for all his Specious talke) will hardly acquit him from a notorious and dangerous defect, and neglect in his Reaſon, and Duty, (for a man may doe all that poſſibly he can, and yet not doe all that's poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be done) nor conſequently can he enſure himſelf of Future Secui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42188:4"/>and Happineſs, (let him pretend never ſo carefully, and conſtantly to follow the cleareſt Light of his own Reaſon) unleſs he can Demonſtrate (which is impoſſible) an impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of diſtinguiſhing true <hi>Guides</hi> from falſe. Neither doe we, in following the Direction of the Church, relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, but punctually obey, our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: we grant, That muſt neceſſarily be Previous, or Introductive, (<hi>i.e.</hi> It ought to direct us to be directed); but when it aſſumes (and this is the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and <hi>Epidemical</hi> Errour) the whole Conduct in every Particular Occurrence to it ſelf, it ceaſeth then to be our <hi>North-Star;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a meer <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> cheating us into dark, and dangerous Pit-falls, and Precipices: To which that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> is very Pertinent, and Applicable; He, that will be his own Teacher, will have a Fool to his Scholar.</p>
            <p>God not-ſeldom permits the Divel to transform himſelf into an Angel of Light, which is an infernal Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, hardly (if poſſibly) diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhable
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42188:4"/>by any private Reaſon, or Induſtry; and therefore the ſame Merciful God, to prevent our being intangled, and caught in ſo enticing, and treacherous a Snare, hath been pleas'd out of his Immenſe care, and love to Man-kind, (for he ordinarily works by ſecondary means,) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe the Perpetual Illumination of the Holy Ghoſt to thoſe, whom he left, under Him, to Guide, Govern, and Inſtruct us concerning all difficulties, we ſhall encounter in our Way to Heaven: So that if we are deceived in being Govern'd, and Rul'd by that Church, which our Bleſſed Saviour hath commanded us (under Penalty of being accounted Heathens, and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans) to obey; He, that can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deceive, nor be deceived, has done it. Which is both falſe, and impoſſible in the higheſt Degree.</p>
            <p>And yet I doe not deny but that God Almighty may ſo immediately irradiate a Soul with Divine Light, as that it may be ſaved without an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termediate Guidance of any Church at all, Fallible or Infallible. But,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42188:5"/>certainly, we muſt not conclude what He Will doe, from what he Can: and for a Man to deſert the Communion, and Direction of the Church, becauſe God (if he pleaſes) can otherwiſe ſave him, would be as deſperate a Preſumption, as for a Man to leap out of a Good Ship into the Sea, becauſe God ſtrengthn'd Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> once, to walk upon the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>God Almighty (no doubt) can ſuſtain a Man without any corporal Nouriſhment at all; but I ſhould think it a madneſs, for all that, in any Perſon to reſolve therefore to Eat no more; or to ſay, that Meat and Drink are not neceſſary for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his Life. Starving would infallibly convince him of his Error, as Perdition will thoſe that wilfully ſeparate from the Church, out of which there is no Salvation: And 'tis no more Uncharitable, or leſs true to affirm this, than to ſay, Thoſe, that were out of <hi>Noah</hi>'s-<hi>Ark</hi> were inevitably, and irrecoverably drown'd in the Deluge: What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42188:5"/>Temerity, and Madneſs can there be, than for a Man to diſobey God's Poſitive Command in hopes of his Favour, and Aſſiſtance ſome other extraordinary way: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>Humane Reaſon,</hi> or (what if I ſay'd?) <hi>Septiciſm;</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian's from that Method, and rejects that irrevocable, and indiſpenſable Injunction, <hi>Harken to the Church,</hi> (be it never ſo ſpeciouſly, and florid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propos'd) can never iſſue from the Father of Lights, but is Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally Created, or Kindled at the Wild-Fire of a Flaſhing Fancy, that can have no longer Duration, or Perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence than Lightning; which in an inſtant vaniſhes. <hi>Submitting our Judgments to Authority, or any thing elſe whatſoever,</hi> (he ſays) <hi>gives <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality, and Perpetuity to Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may Jingle pretily to ſome Ears, that itch after <hi>Novelty,</hi> and <hi>Libertiniſm;</hi> but I ſhall never believe it Rational, unleſs he can Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that the fitteſt thing to hold Water is a Cullender; For he might
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42188:6"/>as well have told me, and as ſolidly (though in plainer Words); If you would keep, and confine the Sea with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it's due Bounds, and Limits, there is no better way in the world, than to dig down the Banks, and demoliſh the Walls, and then you need fear neither Inundation, nor Deluge. <hi>His vertitur Orbis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Man (I know) may ſee the Sky in a Pail of Fair Water, but I never before heard (as he argues) that Heaven was to be ſeen in the Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of a Well; and therefore that ordinary (or rather extraordinary) ſaying of <hi>Democritus,</hi> That Truth lyes in the Bottom of a Deep Well. I muſt confeſs, I doe not well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: and ſo for fear of drowning ſhall let it paſs, as too deep and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a Myſtery for my ſhallow Reaſon to dive, or look into.</p>
            <p>Thus ſome <hi>Criticks</hi> of this Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Age, firſt turn their Brains, and then all things Topſie-turvy; For if this Doctrine of <hi>Democritus</hi> be true, we muſt no longer ſay, Look up, but down, to Heaven; and Pump, or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42188:6"/>draw up Salvation, as they do water in Buckets.</p>
            <p>He needed not, <hi>To have Enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Various Sentiments of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient</hi> Philoſophers, <hi>and no warre en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing. Thence to infer a poſſibility for Chriſtians of different Belief, to live (as to the Exteriour) Harmoniouſly, and Peaceably; For, doubtleſs, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Sects among us, if all the force they uſe to reduce others to their way be (as it ought to be) only perſwaſive, not compulſive, may (as in other diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Countries) move in our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Sphere without claſhing as the Planets do in their Regularly-Irregular Motions:</hi> If this be all he drives at, there's no Difference at all between him and me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether the Reformation</hi> (which he endeavours to vindicate) <hi>were the occaſion of ſo much Bloud, Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and almoſt Deſolation in all thoſe Countries, which admitted</hi> (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were forc'd to) <hi>it;</hi> I ſhall not here diſpute: but 'tis out of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie they actually happen'd; which Diſmal Effects (I muſt confeſs) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42188:7"/>me to believe that God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty's Benediction (for all their ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reaſonings, and Religious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences) never did, or will, goe with it.</p>
            <p>He runs on for ſeveral Pages very wittily, and <hi>Rethorically,</hi> to prove, <hi>That every Mans Particular Reaſon, if well follow'd</hi> (and there's a Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis) <hi>will Infallibly carry him at last, though perhaps through many Tedious, and Troubleſome Wandrings, to his Eternal Happineſs.</hi> Well; I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with this, and ſay ſo too, but withall muſt ask him a Queſtion, Why does not that man well follow his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who in all Doubts and Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, (for certainly ſuch things there are) thinks nothing under Heaven more Rational, than to ſubmit to, and acquieſce in the Interpretation, Definitions, and Decrees of General Councils? If he ſays, Theſe all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may Erre as likely as he, then I ſay, this, to my Reaſon, ſounds as unreaſonably as if he ſhould ſay, One Man may be as ſtrong as ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand: and thus if his own Argument
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42188:7"/>be good, (whether the Victory be on his, or on my ſide) he is equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defeated. I grant, a Chriſtian (though without any Fraction, or Diviſion [for certainly there's no Plurality] in the Radical Unity,) may believe Various Articles by the ſame Act of Faith: for it's Root, or Fountain (although it germinat's, and ſpreads into ſeveral Branches, or runs in various Rivulets) is indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly one and the ſame; (for doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a Man's Faith may encreaſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Variation): but to ſay (as this Author) <hi>That a Man may be to day fully a</hi> Papiſt, <hi>ſeven years hence a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, and then What-he-fancyes-next; and that although be believes things di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly Oppoſite, evidently Contrary,</hi> Pro <hi>and</hi> Con, <hi>or forward and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: Yet if he be all the while Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, and moved by the ſame Soul of Faith,</hi> (which he ſays is Conſcience) <hi>it is ſtill the ſame Numerical Faith.</hi> This I ſay, is ſuch a Prepoſterous piece of Jumbling Divinity, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he may pleaſe himſelf with the Fancy (for that's the very beſt) of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42188:8"/>it; I ſhall never believe the God of Order, and Unity, can Fancy, or be Pleaſed with, ſuch a Deformed ſhape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and Confus'd Variety; He might as well have told me (and I ſhould as ſoon have believ'd him) that a Man, if he be all the while vivify'd, or actuated by the ſame inſtruments of Life (<hi>viz.</hi> Heart and Vitals) though he be ſet juſt upon his Head, he ſtands directly upon his Feet. Tricks of Activity are commendable enough, but certainly 'tis deſperate for a Mans Faith to leape the Sommerſet: And thus, Unity or Sameneſs of Beliefe (ſo often inculcated in Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) is quite thrown out of doors, and Divine Faith reduc'd to a ſtrong (or rather a Weak, and Wavering) Fancy.</p>
            <p>Wherefore allowing <hi>His Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Diſcourſe, about Corporal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to be true</hi> (for I grant in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary Bodies there is, yet without any Alteration, or Change in the Form or <hi>Species,</hi> (as he pretends may be in Faith), a perpetual Flux; and that they muſt neceſſarily Trans-ſpire
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42188:8"/>to make room for new Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;) Yet <hi>I</hi> deny, for the Reaſons aforeſaid, <hi>That only ſuch a Fixt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Variable Identity,</hi> (as he ſpeaks of,) is requiſite to a Man's Faith; Nor truly can <hi>I</hi> perceive any better, or more ſolid Reſult from all his ſurprizing Arguments than this, That ſo Men doe but believe, 'tis no great matter for the What, or the Why.</p>
            <p>He will ſtill have his own <hi>ſole</hi> and <hi>ſingular Reaſon</hi> to Counterballance (if not outweigh) all Eccleſiaſtical Rule and Superiority, (as much as to ſay, The beſt way to ſecure a Ship at Sea is, to take away her Anchor, and Rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,) <hi>For what is it</hi> (ſays he) <hi>you will truſt your Soul with, in this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Buſineſs? Is it the Authority of Men? Theſe verily may lead you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Errour, and 'tis not impoſſible into the worſt and greateſt of all, which is the Deſertion of</hi> Chriſt <hi>himſelf.</hi> Such a Poſſibility, <hi>I</hi> utterly deny, and, for my Confidence and Warrant, produce the ſacred Writ, where the Church is call'd, <hi>The Ground, and Pillar of Truth:</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:42188:9"/>with the Divine Promiſe annext, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which the Gates of Hell, ſhall never prevail:</hi> Now if this Gentleman can ſhew ſuch a Character given, or Promiſe made to his ſolitary Reaſon: I'le ſubmit and beg his Pardon; if he cannot, then he muſt excuſe me for doubting, his Reaſon did not take ſuch Directions as it ought, and might have done before it ſet forth? nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently can he aſcertain me, that 'tis purify'd from all Paſſion, Intereſt, and Senſuality. Pride made the Greateſt Angel a Divel, and a Man's own Reaſon (too far truſted) turns to Madneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Arian Hereſie</hi> (which he hints at) Clouded, but never Totally E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed, or Corrupted the Church, which will ever remain immaculate, and pure: For the <hi>Westerne</hi> Parts felt little, or nothing of that Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Peſtilence, which in leſs than four Years ſhe happily Diſperſed, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipated, as the Sun by Degrees, does Miſt's, and Vapours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As to the Condemnation of</hi> Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, <hi>and whatſoever ſiniſter, or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Christian
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42188:9"/>Proceedings, he chargeth the then</hi>-Pope <hi>with;</hi> If he would vouchſafe to peruſe ſome of our Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, or Modern Controvertiſts (who treat at large of the Sanctions of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils); I preſume, he would clearly, and evidently diſcover his Miſ-information; and that, which he is willing to take for a certain Truth, (for <hi>Quod volumus, facile credimus,</hi>) would prove a meer Calumny, and Impoſture.</p>
            <p>But ſtill, from the wicked Errours of ſome of that Council, he infers a poſſibility, that all might unanimouſly have err'd ſo: <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>This poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Errour (even in ſo high a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,) we ſhall find in the Nature, and very Elements of a Council. For if any one Member of it may be a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, or Atheist in Opinion (as the Lives (he ſays) of many</hi> Popes, <hi>and the Speeches of ſome declare, that they themſelves have been,) why not Two, not Three, not more, not the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Part, that is, The whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though this (<hi>I</hi> Confeſs) be out of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42188:10"/>my Element, yet <hi>I</hi> think the inconſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of it may be Demonſtrated by this Syllogiſm. That which may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to any one egge in the Pariſh may happen to all. But it may happen to any one egge in the Pariſh to goe into a Man's Mouth at once; therefore it may happen to all the Egges in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, to go into a man's mouth at once: Now, Who ſees not the <hi>Aequivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of his <hi>Logick,</hi> which Diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes not between a Diviſive, and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective ſenſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who thoſe Perſons were (which he mentions with ſo much Veneration) of ſuch Excellent Abilities, and worthy Spirits, to examine by the Rules of their own Reaſon, thoſe Follies, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Errours in Religion, I</hi> know not, but am certain thoſe that Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Idolatrous Nations of the World to Chriſtianity, were of that very ſort of Men, who, he is pleas'd to ſay, are firſt taught to think, and then to ſpeak they know not what, <hi>I</hi> mean the Sons of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo that he who charges theſe with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Idolatry, becauſe they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42188:10"/>beg the interceſſion of the Saints, and uſe pious Repreſentations; his Reaſon indeed teaches him firſt to think, and then to ſay, he knows not what: For would it not be wonderful Wiſdom in any man to tell another, that if he has a mind to preſerve the memory of a very dear Friend, he muſt by no means look upon his Picture, (for that would infallibly take his thoughts quite off from him,) but if he ſtares upon the bare Wall, he will there cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly find a very lively and perfect <hi>Idea</hi> of him. <hi>Qui vult decipi, deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piatur.</hi> Undoubtedly the Picture of our Bleſſed Saviour upon the Croſs, is ſo far from making us think of any Strange, or Falſe Gods, that it ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers our vain, and ſcatter'd thoughts together, and makes us more Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly, and Attentively think of Him, to whom we addreſs our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
            <p>What hurt or danger can there be in any thing, which occaſions one to think of our Saviour <hi>Christ,</hi> (as a Picture of his Paſſion very Effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth)? or what Idolatry, when
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42188:11"/>(excited thereby to a Contemplation of our Saviours Crucifixion,) one Bowes towards (not to) the Picture? Do Men worſhip, or adore, any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter pronouncing the word <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> becauſe they doe (or ſhould) Bow at that ſacred Name? Certainly no; me-thinks the very Light of Nature ſhould decide this Controverſie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out more adoe. No Man bowes at thoſe Five Letters, I. E. S. U. S. but becauſe Conjoyn'd, they ſpell the Holy Name of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> So, no Man Bowes at the Subſtance, or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of a Picture of the Paſſion, but becauſe being diſpos'd, and ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow'd by the <hi>Painter's Pencil,</hi> they repreſent our Redeemer dying upon the Croſs: A Picture then is a Word to the Eye, as a word is a Picture to the Ear; and if it be not Idolatry to bow at the Name, (which is but a ſound,) I ſhall never be convinc'd, that 'tis any to bow at the Picture of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> which is but a Shaddow, unleſs it could be prov'd, that all things are ſtrictly forbidden, which are not expreſly commanded. But to our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:42188:11"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Men ought</hi> (he ſays) <hi>to put their Confidence, rather in the Traditions of the former, than the Commands of the preſent Church:</hi> This indeed wants nothing at all but proving; but, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it true, what better means can he poſſibly propoſe to himſelf to know the Truth of former Traditions, than the Sufferage of this preſent Church? But he would have no man build his Belief upon the Authority of paſt, or preſent Ages; (a ſtrange Caution from a ſingle perſon.) <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>If they look upon all the Conſequences of that Opinion,</hi> (it ſeems then all our Fore-fathers were ſtupidly blind) <hi>they are in much greater danger of being drawn from the Chriſtian Faith, than thoſe, who remit the Judgment of theſe things to their own Reaſon:</hi> For God's ſake, why ſo? That certainly now is the true Rule of Faith, which was the Eſſential means of planting, and conſerving it firſt; but Orall, and Apoſtolical Tradition, not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Books, nor any Man's private Spirit, or Reaſon, was the Eſſential means of Planting, and Conſerving it at firſt; therefore Orall, and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42188:12"/>Tradition, not Written Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is ſtill the true, and certain Rule of Faith: And Conſequently this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's <hi>Human Reaſon,</hi> much more likely to draw him from the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith than ſuch a Rule.</p>
            <p>I am glad his Reaſon hath at laſt compell'd him to Believe, that, Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility (let him define it how he will) muſt neceſſarily be annext to our Guide in Spiritual Matters.</p>
            <p>And I ſhould with all my Soul, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce to hear of any means, <hi>That might reſtore the Greatest Part of Man kind</hi> (as he ſays) <hi>into a hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. and comfortable Condition, and that ſo many Millions might not Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally periſh:</hi> But that Dreadful Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>Extra Eccleſiam nulla eſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> turns my hope into fear, and trembling; for though ignorance perhaps may very much Extenuate, or excuſe; yet if an Errour be Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental, that ignorance (though never ſo invincible,) cannot after it's Nature, or quality; nor acquit the Profeſſor from all Guilt, and Penalty; for he, that unawares drops
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42188:12"/>into the Water, (if he be Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd,) is as certainly drown'd, as he that willfully plunges himſelf in, over Head and Eares. And I fear, the reward of invincible Ignorance, may be rather an Abatement of Puniſhment, than a Fruition of Bliſs.</p>
            <p>Errours in Faith, (at leaſt Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental,) I conceive to be of a more pernicious Conſequence, than (at preſent) a vitiou, Life; for no Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Man (I think) queſtions but that 'tis better for a Man to Loyter, or Stumble, nay to fall and hurt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a right Path; than to walk Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly (I mean with Moral Honeſty) in a wrong. As there is more hopes certainly of the Salvation of a ſinful Chriſtian, than a Religious <hi>Jew;</hi> the former being ſtill in the Road poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to recover, and perſevere Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently, and Proſperouſly; the latter be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing totally incapacitated through the Eccentrical Crookedneſs of his way to make a good, or happy Period of his ill begun Progreſs.</p>
            <p>There may be ſeveral wayes to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42188:13"/>ſame Faith, but certainly <hi>Not ſeveral Faiths</hi> (as this Author imagines) to the ſame GOD, who is an Indiviſible, and Immutable Eſſence; &amp; therefore, Going-vigorouſly-forward, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies nothing, unleſs we goe right: He that wills the End, muſt neceſſarily uſe the means. So that this Author can never win me to his Opinion, that all Men (though never ſo Diſcrepant in their Faith, following in all Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars the Dictates of their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Reaſon,) will infallibly in the end arrive at Security, and Happineſs; till he hath proved, that the Way, which leads a Man directly to <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> (if he that travels in it confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently believes he's right,) will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly bring him to <hi>Dover. Crede quod habes, et habes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He had rather think</hi> (he ſays) <hi>with</hi> Origen, <hi>that the Divels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the exceſſive kindneſs of their Judge, ſhall at last be exempted from Damnation, than that he himſelf, ſhall be damn'd for that Opinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Undoubtedly, this ſhews the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42188:13"/>to be a very Compaſſionate, and good Natur'd Man; but certainly that cannot be true Charity, which 'thwarts the irrevocable Decree of Heaven; and truly I do not ſee, why he may not (with as much Reaſon) doubt that the Glorify'd Bodyes may fall from their Beatitude, as think, that the Divels themſelves ſhall at laſt be releas'd from their Damnation: but as, certainly, the former are paſt all hopes of Relaxation: from their Torments, ſo the latter are paſt all fear of being depriv'd of their Felicity and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Jubilee. For that which truly makes Heaven and Hell, is not ſo much the exceſſive Greatneſs, as Infinity of their Joyes, and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>He thinkes, <hi>He may very well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that there are Secret and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful ways, by which</hi> GOD <hi>may be pleaſed to apply his Merits to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind beſides, thoſe direct, open and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ones of Baptiſm, and Confeſſion.</hi> This <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſs is very ſecret, wonderful, and dark Divinity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Diametrically oppoſite to the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42188:14"/>Divine Writ, where <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering <hi>Nicodemus</hi> his Queſtion, ſaid poſitively; <hi>Amen, Amen, I ſay to thee, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs a Man be born again of Water and the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of</hi> GOD.</p>
            <p>And therefore why this Author ſhould advance a Beliet ſo palpably <hi>Anti-Christian; I</hi> cannot imagine, unleſs he ſuppoſes (which is Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to think) that our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our did not then fully underſtand his own mind. The Text clearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes the Extravagancy, and impiety of ſuch an imagination, and diſcovern this Authors <hi>Human Reaſon</hi> to be in this, (as in many other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,) but a fallacious Dream, from which if he would rouſe, and thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly awake himſelf, he would quickly perceive it to vaniſh into nothing, and prove a meer Illuſion; For <hi>I</hi> leave any Prudent Chriſtian to judge, whether he thinks it not onely abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to walk towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by thoſe Direct, Open, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary wayes of Baptiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but alſo abſolutely impoſſible, (unleſs in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42188:14"/>caſe of Martyrdom, which is ſtill Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm in Bloud), to croſs over upon ſuch a ſlight, and ſlippery Bridge as this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Author think's (without proving) that there may be other ſecret, and wonderful ways of ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thither: And he may (if he pleaſe) goe one Step farther, and believe, that there may be no other ſecret, and wonderful ways for a man to live, beſides Breathing: <hi>Corruptio optimi peſſima.</hi> And certainly that muſt need's be an impious exceſs of Charity, which not onely ſhakes the Foundation, but fruſtrates the whole Fabrick, and Deſigns of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. GOD deliver all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians from ſuch gentle, and good-Natur'd Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Our Bleſſed Saviour (that beſt knew) foretold, there muſt be <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi> which moſt Divines agree to be thoſe Gates of Hell mentioned in Scripture, and conſequently in-lets to Damnation: Contrary to which this Author contends, that ſcarce any <hi>Hereſie</hi> (if at all diſcoverable) can be Damnable, and maintains ſuch a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42188:15"/>Facility to avoid all dangerous Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, that no Men of ordinary Senſe, and Reaſon can poſſibly fall into them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haereticum hominem poſt unam, &amp; ſecundam correptionem</hi> (the Scripture ſaith) <hi>devita.</hi> But how can he be ſhun'd, that is not knowable? And therefore, I muſt intreat this Author to correct Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s Admonition, or his own <hi>Human Reaſon</hi> (which, he thinks fit,) for one of them cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly is very much in fault.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To obey in matters of Belief with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being able to believe the thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, is no leſs</hi> (he ſays), <hi>and ſeems more a Contradiction, than ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to obey without knowledge of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</hi> Certainly this Author thinks every Man's Reaſon has a ſecret, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Power to attract, or draw down the high Myſteries of Faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in view of his Underſtanding, which is impoſſible: But if Men's Reaſons are (as beyond Debate they may be) ſatisfy'd, that thoſe who guide them, neither will, nor can deceive; what ſhould make them ſtart, or fly back?
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42188:15"/>Their incapacity to underſtand can be no good, or ſufficient Reaſon for them to disbelieve, and a much worſe Argument to prove any thing <hi>(de fide)</hi> falſe, which they propoſe, who doe truly, and Naturally conveigh to us, the Will, and Pleaſure of GOD; they are his Voice, <hi>(Qui vos audit me audit,)</hi> or at leaſt the very <hi>Eccho</hi> of it The Church never Doctrinal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (but when, and what CHRIST) ſpeaks, and if he, that hears one, hears both (which our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſaith) <hi>Human Reaſon</hi> (which thus far ought to proceed, and we to follow) tells us, Our buſineſs, and duty then is to obey, and not diſpute. Beſides, if that ſaying be true, <hi>Fides est Argumentum non-apparentium,</hi> I do not ſee why Faith, and Obedience, ſhould ſtand ſtill, becauſe Reaſon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not go forward.</p>
            <p>He ſays, <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church is broken, not ſo much by them who differ in Opinions, as by them, who will not allow ef ſuch a Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us contrarium verum est:</hi> By
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42188:16"/>this <hi>I</hi> ſee, Reaſon has her <hi>Antipodes</hi> too; for, Can any thing be more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt it, than to call him the greateſt Wrangler, who would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent others from quarrelling? And to ſay, he that would reconcile Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and hinder Men from going to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the Eares, was the occaſion of their falling out? Certainly 'tis as Rational to ſay, There can be no Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, where there's no Confuſion, as to ſay, There can be no Unity, without Difference: 'Tis a Soleciſme, and <hi>Paradox</hi> much above the reach of my Reaſon; but if be underſtands it, 'tis well enough.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who knowes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>whether that</hi> GOD, <hi>who liked best that no Men's Bodyes ſhould have the ſame complexion, no Men's Faces the ſame Figures, no Hares the ſame Lines, no Voyces the ſame Sounds; nay, not ſo much but their Motions, and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures ſhould be Diſtinguiſhable; has not likewiſe beſt pleaſed himſelf with no leſs Variety in the parts of Men, that are Immaterial, and even in the moſt Immaterial Actions of thoſe parts,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42188:16"/>which is the Worſhip, and Adoration of a</hi> Deity.</p>
            <p>This (though it look prettily up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Paper) is a meer <hi>Quick-Sand,</hi> and eaſily anſwer'd with asking ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Queſtion, Who knows whether GOD is beſt pleaſed with ſuch Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety in the Faith, as in the Faces of Men? That which fortifies me, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitably to believe the contrary, are thoſe expreſs Words of Scripture, One GOD, one Faith, one Baptiſm, which evidently inferre, that beſides that General Impediment (<hi>viz.</hi> the Sinfulneſs, and Frailty of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (men, if ſway'd ſolely by their own reaſon) eaſily may, and too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently do, miſcarry, for want of a Right Path.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Does</hi> GOD (ſays he) <hi>gain any thing by our Devotions? does he receive Hurt from one kind of Worſhip, and Advantage by another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No ſurely, (ſay I) for he is an Unutterable Plenitude of Bliſs, and Delectation to Himſelf; but 'tis as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true, that he may be pleas'd with one kind of Worſhip, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42188:17"/>an other; unleſs <hi>Jeroboam</hi> (who, the Holy Scripture more than once ſaith, made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted no Crime, nor conſequently offended GOD, in ſetting up the <hi>Calves</hi> in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Without doubt</hi> (ſaith he, but that's no proof) <hi>He who gave Rules, which might accept of ſeveral Interpretations, when he might have made them as plain to all in one Senſe, as they ſeem now to every man in his own, is likewiſe well contented, that they ſhall be Interpreted ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly, if our Bleſſed Saviour had not Conſtituted Select Judges, and Expoſitors of his Divine Laws (which no Laws ever were without) I might perhaps be of his mind too; but ſince (GOD be thanked) 'tis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently otherwiſe; without doubt this Author is egregiouſly miſtaken. Certainly GOD Almighty (if he had intended Reaſon to be abſolute Lord <hi>Paramount,</hi> independently to Rule, and Inſtruct in every particular Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, &amp; Ambiguity), muſt have given all Men the ſame meaſure to compaſs the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42188:17"/>ſame end. For, as a Ship, though it lies in the Water, if it has not enough to make it Float, can no more move forward, than if it lay upon dry Land: So it can never ſink into my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, How he, that has leſs Reaſon, ſhould as ſafely, and effectually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, as he that has more, unleſs this Author could prove a part of any thing to be as much as the whole, or demonſtrate Reaſon to be of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Nature of the <hi>Manna,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> whereof he who gather'd much had nothing over, and he who gather'd little, had no lack.</p>
            <p>Were this ſeriouſly conſider'd, I am confident upon ſecond Thoughts, (and they are beſt), this Author would be convinc'd, that a Man's Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alone can never doe the Work, I mean ſteer him ſecurely (over that deep Ocean of Scripture), to the Port of Eternal Happineſs, without Embarking in that <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Ship, the Church; in which (if they Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to her Doctrine), the Poor are as ſafe as the Richeſt, and the Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42188:18"/>as the Wiſe: and in this Reliance we doe no more deſert our own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than a Man does his Corporal Strength, in taking a Staffe to help, and ſupport him in a dangerous, and ſlippery Paſſage: And whatever Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments are advanc'd to enervate the ſolidity of this Ground, (let them never ſo briskly ſally out,) they can be no better, than meer emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ebullitions or Bubblings of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As well</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Mud by growing hard, as the Wax by Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, obeys the Sun; nor is it leſs glorify'd by the one, than by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true the ſame Sun (and I grant 'tis equally (though variouſly) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd by both,) ſoftens Wax, and hardens Mud; (their Natures being by Heat to melt, and grow hard,) but I cannot conceive how the Parity holds exactly between thoſe Inani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, material Subſtances, and our Immortal, and Immaterial Souls: For certainly the Divine Inſuſer of Faith, created them with Identical
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42188:18"/>Capabilities, and fitted them Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formly for the Reception of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Objects, <hi>viz.</hi> the Myſteries of Chriſtianity, which whoſoever Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately Diſ-believes, or rejects, is deſervedly Excommunicated, (becauſe he wilfully exclude himſelf) from that Myſticall Ark the Church of GOD.</p>
            <p>But, by the way (me-thinkes) this Author talkes very incongruouſly of more than one Religion, the very word bearing witneſs againſt him; for the Subſtantive <hi>Religio,</hi> I take to be deriv'd from the Verb <hi>Rebigo</hi> to Tye or Bind together; but his <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinarian,</hi> or <hi>Socinian</hi> Doctrine, does not onely Untie and Unbind, but Blends, and Shuffles all into a <hi>Chaos: Yet Faith with him must ſtill be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly one, and the ſame; though ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſe Receptions</hi> (ſays he) <hi>it produces not only divenſe; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Effects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I ſhall believe, when he hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, that, becauſe all things, which are potable are comprehended under the Denomination of Liquour; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42188:19"/>White-Wines, Rheniſh, Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Claret, Syder, and Muſcadine; are Certainly, that Man would be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd to have drunk too much of theſe, that could be brought to ſwallow ſo great a Contradiction: Yet this the Author muſt ſay, (if he ſpeakes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to his own Arguments,) is as defenſible as his Hyperbole, that the Diverſity of Religious Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions (becauſe injuriouſly produc'd by him under the Venerable Name of Faith,) are not ſeveral, but one and the very ſelf ſame belief: which certainly is as far from right Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as a Confuſion of Fancyes is from purely Divine Faith.</p>
            <p>I ſhould have found no fault with <hi>His comparing the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of God's Church to Wed-lock;</hi> but that he ſpoyles the Similitude in allowing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Particular Member to believe contrary to one another, nay to themſelves: by which he pulls down again what he built up; and makes that Conjunction-Disjunctive, by a new-found-Negative, or Counter-Creed.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:42188:19"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>No body at all queſtions, but that a Foot when it hath the Gout,</hi> (as he ſayes,) <hi>or a Hand when it ſhakes with the Palſie, remain ſtill Parts of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: but if they are Irrecoverably uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, they are no otherwiſe ſo, than as a Dead Bough is a Member of a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Tree, there may be Continuity, but no Communication between them; and this Debility, or decay, muſt needs happen through ſome ſecret Perverſity, or Obliquity in the Recipient, not any Defect or Deficiency in the Radical A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liment.</hi> The ſame I ſay of thoſe that wilfully perſiſt in Incredulity, and Errour; but yet withall muſt add this, that they are never Irrevoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly (GOD's Grace being ever bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,) Anathematiz'd by this Church; which is much more willing, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy upon Submiſſion, and Recantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Re-embrace, than for Obſtinacy to Excommunicate any.</p>
            <p>There may certainly be (though he thinks otherwiſe,) a full, and intire agreement in all Points of Faith, of one Member with an other, either Actually or Votively, (which to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42188:20"/>GOD is <hi>Aequivalent,</hi>) or elſe the <hi>Athanaſian Creed</hi> (admitted by moſt Proteſtants,) is not to be Credited, which, without <hi>Haeſitation;</hi> begins thus;</p>
            <p>Whoſoever will be ſaved, it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful before all things that he hold the Catholick Faith; The which unleſs each one ſhall keep whole and Inviolate, (mark that,) he ſhall without doubt eternally periſh; now, if this be (as certainly it is) true, he that wilfully disbelieves any one Article, forfeits his whole Faith, and Conſequently the leaſt Defect therein is a total Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Now as for Controverſie (at which he briefly touches,) like the Bloud (I know) it inceſſantly Circulates; but Alas! To no better purpoſe, that I can perceive, than to foment the Quarrel, and keep it ſtill alive: For through the Immoderation, and Unnatural heat of ſome <hi>Polemick</hi> Writers, 'tis ſo far from effecting a Reconciliation or Union, (which ought to be the Principal Deſign and end of it,) that it do's nothing elſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42188:20"/>but breed an Implacable, if not incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Itch; the ſcratching whereof may, perhaps, afford ſome preſent Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillation or Delight; but 'tis uſually perform'd with ſo much violence, and rage, that it does not only not allay, but more inflame, and ferment the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; to cure which, there is no Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine more Effectual, or <hi>Balſome</hi> more Soveraign, than our Mutual, and Cordiall Prayers, for one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. But, to purſue our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As for thoſe Men</hi> (ſays he) <hi>who accuſe us of Pride, and Vanity, for At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing ſo much to our own Reaſon, making Preſumption. and Self-Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, the Fountain of this Opinion; it is a Scandal ſo falſe, and ſo Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, that without much Humility I ſhould diſdain to anſwer it.</hi> And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in my Opinion, I have not heard a louder ſound of Pride, than in that very Expreſſion. But, letting this paſs, (with his Subſequent, ſoft Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, for the Civility, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs of his Religion, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits every man to have his full Swing,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42188:21"/>or Career) I am come to Maſter <hi>Hob</hi>'s, for whom, though it is not my buſineſs, nor deſign to be Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate, nor in the leaſt to diminiſh this Author's merit; (who, in ſome parts of his Diſcourſe againſt him, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, ſhewes great Fertility of Wit, and Pregnancy of <hi>Rhethorick</hi>): Yet I cannot but think Maſter <hi>Hobs</hi>'s Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments much more Conducing to Order, and Uniformity, than his Unreaſonably-Rational, or Chimae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Method; which ſlighting all <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiastical</hi> Tribunals, authoriſeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Particular Perſon, in Spirituals to be his own Judge, and Paſtor; and makes the Governours of the Church of CHRIST ſtand for meer Cyphers, which is directly againſt the Inſtitution, Doctrine, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of CHRIST himſelf: But, that-<hi>Humane Reaſon,</hi> which exalts it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf above this Divine Juriſdiction, (be it never ſo full of Flouriſhes, and Aſtoniſhment) is but a glorious No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>He is very apt to miſtake, <hi>Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the</hi> Roman-<hi>Church:</hi> For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42188:21"/>indeed her Publick <hi>Liturgie</hi> (the <hi>Maſs</hi>) be Univerſally ſaid in the <hi>Latine</hi> Tongue, yet all Preaching, and Catechizing, is performed in the Language of each reſpective Country; and all her Members without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, ſay their Prayers in their own Native Language.</p>
            <p>I am not at all ſatisfy'd, <hi>With his endeavouring to Diſtinguiſh between Right Reaſon, and that which is falſty eſteemed ſo;</hi> For, if in all matters of Faith, and Difficulty, every Man's Reaſon muſt be his Rule, and every man's Rule muſt be his Reaſon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out adhering or ſubmitting to any other Superior Regulation or Judge, or Captivating his Underſtanding (as Scripture requires) <hi>in Obſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Fidei:</hi> If this Rule (I ſay) can be thought Regular and ſafe, then I think this Author needs not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of bringing men by Degrees to believe, That nothing can be in ſo Rational or Credible, which is not evidently ſo to whom 'tis propos'd; eſpecially ſince he has already affirm'd (which is pretty well towards it)
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42188:22"/>that nothing can be dangerouſly Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, that a man firmly believes. But can any thing be more Illogical and diſtant from Reaſon? Unleſs it be this which <hi>(per Conſequens)</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows; Every <hi>Orthodox</hi> Divine is a Rational Man; <hi>Ergo,</hi> every Rational Man is an <hi>Orthodox</hi> Divine, and ought not to be taught, but to teach himſelf. Contrary to which. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20. our Bleſſed Saviour commanded his Diſciples to goe Preach, Teach, and Baptize all Nations. But I never read that they ſent the Scriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to the Unconverted, that they might, by the Rules of their own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon examine, and frame out the True Religion; but, withall, went them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or ſent Expoſitors: With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, I never heard of <hi>Turk,</hi> or <hi>Jew</hi> that ever chang'd his <hi>Alcoran,</hi> or <hi>Talmud</hi> for the Chriſtian <hi>Bible;</hi> which evidently demonſtrates againſt this Author, <hi>That Reaſon alone can be no Competent means, or ſecurity ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of becoming, or remaining a good Chriſtian.</hi> All Men therefore are, or ſhould be, inſtructed: We are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42188:22"/>Taught, and they were Ttaught the ſame, who Teach us; and their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters had Teachers, and thoſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Maſters, till we come Gradually to the Supream, the Original Guides of the Preſent Church, which alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the Traditions of the former; and ſo orderly downward till we come to the Apoſtles; and at laſt to (our <hi>Ne plus ultra,</hi>) our Saviour CHRIST himſelf: So that 'tis no Contradiction but a certain Truth, that there is no going to CHRIST, but from CHRIST. <hi>à JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> ad CHRIST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M: That Humane Reaſon,</hi> then, which unlinckes it ſelf from this Divine, and Infallible Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catenation, flyes giddily about, and can no more naturally ſettle, or fix, than a Feather in the Wind; and that a man, who ſtubbornly ſteps aſide from this Univerſal, this General Track, will not onely loſe his Way, but his Reaſon, and Himſelf too. But, now, to another Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Henry <hi>the Eighth, did certainly more than ſeem</hi> (as this Author ſays)
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42188:23"/>
               <hi>to leave the</hi> Pope, <hi>becauſe he would not conſent to his Libidinous Deſires; and aſſum'd therefore the Supremacy, that he might give himſelf leave to Marry, or Repudiate what Wives he fancy'd, or diſlik'd.</hi> But although <hi>Abbeys, Monaſteries,</hi> and <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi>-Houſes were thereupon demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and the Profits, and Revenues converted to Secular Uſes. I cannot think, he got any great Advantage by the Bargain, (either to Body, or Soul,) who dy'd with a <hi>Perdidimus Omnia</hi> in his Mouth; and found by Wofull Experience, That in the end, ther's nothing got by Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. But to leave this Digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>The Author <hi>deſires thoſe, who would have his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, to convince him, First, by theirs, that it ought to be ſo, and not to think to enſlave his Reaſon, till they firſt overcome it; which when they have done, then they will loſe what they contend for; For by our Reaſon's being Guided, Conquered, and Enſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, Their</hi>'s <hi>are become Guides, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42188:23"/>and Maſters; ſo that it will appear at laſt impoſſible for</hi> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Reaſon <hi>to loſe anything in one place, without gaining as much in ſome other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus he. To which I anſwer in the firſt place, If Scripture be Reaſon, our Underſtandings ought to be cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated to the Obedience of Faith. In the next, I would not have him think us ſo unreaſonable, as to deprive men Totally of the Uſe of their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: by no means, but to check, and keep it within it's proper Sphear, and in this we abridge him of no Liberty, which we allow our ſelves.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Humane Reaſon</hi> muſt have a large Mixture of Divinity in it, to be ſo Adorable as this Author ſeems to make it. I grant 'tis very pretious, and prizable in being given (though not Magiſterially to rule) to guide us to thoſe, that can Infallibly do it: And thus (I confeſs) we are Rul'd by Reaſon, though not in all things by our own; for all the Difficulties, and Obſcurities of Scripture without
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42188:24"/>the Churche's Light, are no more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretable, or Diſcoverable by Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Reaſon, than our Eyes can ſee Objects without Day-Light, or a Candle; and yet neither our Reaſon, nor our Eyes are given us in vain: But he that, in Spiritual Affairs, which ſo neerly concern bis Soul, Aſſigns no Viſible, no External, rule or Standard to meaſure Reaſon by, nor any Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Touch-Stone to try True, from Falſe, Adulterated from Currant Coyne; That Man, I ſay (for all his pretended Light within,) fiſhes in the Dark with them, that labour'd all Night and caught nothing; or builds his Superſtructure before he lays the Foundation. For 'tis as Irrational as if a Man ſhould ſay, I can gueſſe ſo exactly of the <hi>Longitude, Latitude, Altitude,</hi> and <hi>Profunditie</hi> of any thing by my Eye, that no Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration by any <hi>Mathematical</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments can (or ever ſhall) Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul, or Convince me: And truly what better has this Author ſaid from the beginning to the Ending of his Treatiſe than this, That Mens Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42188:24"/>and Judgements (as to the Regulation of their Faith) are ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cleer, and Demonſtrative, that there is no certain way, no poſſibility to know whether they be true, or falſe, right, or wrong: Turne it which way you will, this is all you ſhall find in it; which Unreaſonable Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning verifyes the Old Proverb, <hi>[All is not Gold that Glisters:]</hi> And in Truth, if each Man's Reaſon (Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſculouſly) muſt be Umpire in this Rational Strife, men may Play at this Sport to Perpetuity and never win nor loſe: But certainly our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour has not left the Condition of Mankind in this endleſs Confuſion, but has miraculouſly Founded, and Signaliz'd a Church to end all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſyes, if Men (that talk ſo much of Reaſon,) would but rightly uſe it; for that Reaſon, which (as to Spirituality) does not take the Church for it's Reſt, can never aim, or hit right, but muſt neceſſarily fly at Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſpend it elſe without Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If that Authority</hi> (ſays he) <hi>which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42188:25"/>we Obey, preſcribe Truth, we have Good Fortune in our Obedience, and meerly Good Fortune; but, if it draw us into Errours, we have nothing to ſay for our Excuſe, becauſe we have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to Alledge for our Obedience to that Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems then, that our Saviour's Commands are of no Validity, and, Hearken to, and Obey the Church meer Fopperies; but certain it is CHRIST our Lord has moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, and Emphatically enjoyn'd this; and therefore we may (nay muſt) without any If's, abſolutely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it; and this queſtionleſs will be a very good, and ſufficient <hi>Plea</hi> for our Obedience at the Day of Judgement, How thoſe, who ſlight it, would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe themſelves, (were there to be any Pleading at that Grand-Aſſize;) cannot imagine, but am certain, if they come off well, they will have Extraordinary good Fortune in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
            <p>His following Diſcourſe, <hi>Of Mens Blind-folding themſelves</hi> (as he blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calls it,) <hi>in obeying Eccleſiaſticall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42188:25"/>Superiours; and that thoſe, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves to the Guidance of their own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, are as ſafe on the Left Hand, as on the Right;</hi> (but who can credit this, That knowes one Hand from the other?) As ſecure of Happineſs in their Errours (very ſtrange!) as others, who are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe guilded even in the Truths, which they happen to fall into; is ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagantly Frivolous, and proofleſs, that it carryes it's own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation with it. <hi>&amp; ſic Tranſeat to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Commands no more but to ſearch, and yet ſhall find whether the Truth or not,</hi> (Ipſe Dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it) <hi>the Reward of Searching. And truly I have endeavour'd, and narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſearch'd to find Reaſon in this. But after all my Diligence, can perceive no Reward of my Searching; which makes me conclude, That 'tis much more Rational to believe, that</hi> GOD <hi>gives Man not only a Will to ſearch, but Power to find, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding to know the Truth when found; or elſe his Commands were vain.</hi> But what a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42188:26"/>Deſperate, long Leap doe's this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor leave between Searching, and Heaven! If it were as he imagines, I doe not ſee why a man's Heartily wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf there, might not bring him, or waft him thither, without more adoe, and Eternal Happineſſe be given him as a reward of wiſhing. But undoubtedly finding the Truth is the reward of Searching, and Heaven the reward of finding the Truth; which thoſe, who ſearch where it is not, ſhall find nothing but anxiety, and in the end, that they wretchedly cheated themſelves, and others with ſhippery <hi>Sophiſm</hi>'s, and <hi>Chimaera's</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As no men are ſav'd but through Mercy, ſo none unjuſtly Periſh; for, Truth is miſſed, not ſo much through Difficulty of Finding, as Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity, and Negligence in ſearching it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I cannot poſſibly</hi> (ſays the Author) <hi>conceive it agreeable to the Goodneſs of the Divine Nature ſo to have hidden, and involved, and almoſt diſguiſed the Truth from us, if he had intended to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42188:26"/>have cenſured the miſſing of it, with ſo heavy a Sentence, as that of Eternal Ruine; eſpecially, ſeeing there is but one true Way,</hi> (I thought, All ways had been alike with him, as to the end) <hi>for one Hundred falſe ones, and no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Mark ſet upon the Entry of that One, to Diſtinguiſh it from the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer; If GOD Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, had left us a Way without any Means or Marks, (as he ſtrangely imagines) to find it out, it would be great Cruelty indeed in him, (which is far enough from his Nature,) to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Men Eternally, for what is not in their Power poſſibly to avoyd: But ſince 'tis moſt evident, that he hath left both ſufficient means to find, and Marks to know it by; his Diſcourſe upon this Point, is (in my Opinion) only juſt ſo many Words to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And ſince thoſe Marks, which are ſet upon the Entry of this Way, are moſt clear, and conſpicuous to all Men, that look not Obliquely upon them; if (after they are entred) they meet with any thing, that Reaſon may
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42188:27"/>perhaps at firſt, Flinch, or Boggle at, the Conſideration of it's, Inerrability takes away all doubt, and bids them confidently perſevere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As in Viſible Objects,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>we Receive confidently, and reſt in the Report of the Sight,</hi> &amp;c. So ought we as entirely, and abſolutely, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign our Belief, to the Dictates of our own Underſtanding, in things intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, which are as Properly, and Naturally the Objects thereof, as things viſible are of the Eye-Sight: and we might as well ſay, We will truſt our Eyes in Green, White, and Black, but not in Red, or Yellow Collours: as affirm, <hi>That our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt Guide us in the Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Nature, the Search of Arts, the Government of Publick Societies, and the Begulation of Mens Lives, as far as the Bounds of Morality; but that it is not at all to be Followed, or O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd in Matters that concern Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I muſt confeſs, the Author has ſome Colour, but I think not much Reaſon, for what he ſays: For
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42188:27"/>if he thinks the Objects of Faith, are as Naturally Intelligible by our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as the Colours of the <hi>Rain-Bow,</hi> are viſible to our Eyes; he makes no Diſtinction, or Difference at all, between the Faculties, Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or Effects of Nature, and thoſe of Grace, which certainly is a Grand Miſtake. For although our own Reaſon or underſtanding tell us, There is a God, and He to be Worſhipp'd, and Obey'd by us; yet they cannot by their own Light, or inward Forces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us, In what manner, that muſt be done by External Agents, by ſome thing which is without us. And what imaginably more probable, than the Church of Chriſt, which can ſhew a Lineal Succeſſion, from the ſame Chriſt, and His Apoſtles; a Perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Viſibility, Unity, Univerſality, Converſion of Nations, Fulfilling of Propheſies, (which baffles all Cavils, and ſtrikes all Objections dumb,) a Miraculous Propagation. Now he who prefers the Dictates of his own Private and naked Reaſon, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, in matters that concern
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42188:28"/>Religion, before the Guidance of a Church thus Adorn'd, thus Mark'd, thus Signaliz'd, deſerves not (nor truly has he) either the one, or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Nothing certainly can be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <hi>to</hi> Humane Reaſon, <hi>than to think we ought to believe nothing above it:</hi> For there are Truth's Un-intelligible, by the moſt Exalted, and Sublimated Souls in Heaven, <hi>viz.</hi> The Total, and Perfect Quality of the Divine Eſſence; which, nothing Created, nothing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to God himſelf, can Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend. The Saints and Angels, enjoy Eternity without knowing what it is; the moſt Towring Wiſdom, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purated Reaſon, can no more reach, or fathom, that Inſcrutable Infinity, than Ten Millions of Oceans can be crowded into the ſmalleſt Cockle-Shell: For it drowns, or rather (as a Bottomleſs <hi>Abyſſe</hi>), ſwallows up all <hi>Philoſophy</hi> and Learning. 'Tis the <hi>Philoſophers-Stone</hi> in Divinity, too hard to be Penetrated, by the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Men or Angels: In fine, We know that ſuch a thing there is, but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:42188:28"/>never ſhall, it's full, and perfect Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, it being no leſs, than the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Tri-Une God; whoſe Deep. brief Character of Himſelf was, <hi>Sum qui Sum.</hi> Whence I inferr, That Men are not endued with Underſtanding, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly to ſtretch beyond it's Strength, and Power, or to uſe it, as they themſelves liſt: But according to the Will and Pleaſure of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Donor;</hi> who certainly gives Man Reaſon, not abſolutely, but Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally; that in Matters of Faith (at leaſt) it ſhould retribute, and pay Homage to Him, I mean be Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by His <hi>Beloved Spouſe,</hi> the <hi>Church.</hi> For as that is no true Liberty, which has no Limit, ſo that is no true Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which has no Reſtriction. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if moſt Men are allowed, and granted to have Reaſon, certainly the Church do's not want it, <hi>(Vis unita fortior),</hi> but has in it a more Ample, Perfect, and incorrigible manner, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe: more immediately, and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally accompanyed and Aſſiſted by the Holy Ghoſt. And this is true, nay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly true, if Scripture be not falſe.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42188:29"/>How thoſe Headleſs-Members, the <hi>Acephaliſts,</hi> would anſwer here, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell; but am certain, that, As that is not true Reaſon, but Deluſion, which flowes not from the right Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; So, a Viſible Congregation, or Body of Men, without a Viſible Head, or with more than one, is equally Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous. But thoſe Spiritual Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers, who ſlight the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy,</hi> or <hi>Convoy,</hi> contemn the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church; and reſolve to believe no more, than their Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings can Chew, and their Reaſon Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, (there being many things in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which poſe Mortality; as the Flux, and Re-flux of the Sea, the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Loud-Stone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) will live <hi>Infidels,</hi> and dye <hi>Atheiſts.</hi> Nor is this ſaid, To remove the Cognizance of Divine Truths, out of the Court of Reaſon; but to quell it's Pride and Arrogance, and bring it to (Submit, and ſtoop by an Humble Faith to thoſe Divine Truths; (for certainly a mans Reaſon, may Rebell againſt his Faith, as well as his Paſſion, againſt Reaſon) and this Limitation or Coaction, does
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42188:29"/>not at all deprive man of his Power, nor abridge him of the Liberty, and natural priviledge of Election, or Choice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Religion, ſays he, appears</hi> (and what Chriſtian dares deny it?) <hi>to be the Principal End of mans Creation; and therefore as if</hi> Horſes <hi>are made for Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, they have a Natural ability gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, where-with to do it; If Birds do fly, they have Wings given them for that purpoſe; (becauſe where an end is Natural, the means are ſo too:) So if Religion be the End of Man, as he is Partaker of a Rational Soul, that Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Soul hath ſome Power naturally, placed in it, for the excerciſe, judgment, and choice of Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this is Undeniably true: But yet the Author may pleaſe to conſider, That the <hi>Horſe</hi> may be over-loaded, and the Bird fly too high; and ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Reaſon may ſoar above it's Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Pitch, <hi>Meridian Altitude,</hi> and Conſequently into a <hi>Region,</hi> where 'tis a mere Stranger, and cannot ſubſiſt without ſome ſtronger Principle, than it's own proper Strength to ſupport
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42188:30"/>it: And ſo, granting the Antecedent, I deny the Conſequence; That becauſe GOD gives man Reaſon (as I have ſaid) to light or introduce him into the right Entrance of Religion; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (being once initiated) he needs not to ask any more queſtions, or be guided by others: but let him follow his own Reaſon, (I might as well have ſaid his Noſe.), and he cannot poſſibly go aſtray. Briefly; In the Search, or Choice of our Way, Reaſon (I grant) muſt rule, but that once found, Obey: For that private Spirit, which is not firſt quickned, or animated, and then conſtantly Actuated, by that of God's Church, (which was Authoriz'd, and Sanctify'd by the Divine Breath of JESUS) is a Falſe Conception, no true, or lawful Iſſue of the Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but a <hi>Spurious,</hi> or <hi>Abortive Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brion</hi> of the Brain; a Falle Light, a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful <hi>Phantaſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Author ſays, <hi>If this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> (<hi>that is for every Man to believe</hi> ad libitum) <hi>were Generally planted in the Minds of men, both the Reality, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42188:30"/>Pretence of Fighting for Religion, were utterly Cancell'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly ſo far I ſhould like his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, eſpecially if he could warrant men, that Intellectual or Religious Differences, ſhould never come to Blowes: But Alas! Experience makes me more than doubt, 'tis but an Airy, or imaginary Notion: For, as I do not deny, but that thoſe who endeavour an Eſtabliſhment of Unity, and Uniformity in Faith, and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may poſſibly occaſion War; So thoſe (I fear) of contrary Principles, can never long prevent it; But, I hope that GOD, who rules the unruly O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, will.</p>
            <p>Thus far I do moſt willingly agree with him; That I would have none, who diſturbe not the publick peace, &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of the Government, be perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon a purely conſcientious ſcore: For, I think it a moſt uncharitable, and unreaſonable method, (becauſe impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) to reduce mens Judgments, ('tis but one remove, from convincing them with Beetles, and Halters), by taking away their Eſtates, and Starving
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42188:31"/>their Bodies; But againſt thoſe, who are found any way machinating againſt our true, and lawful Governours, (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the Supream), with all Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Rigour, <hi>Currat Lex.</hi> But yer, let every man ſmart, for his proper Fault; and not a whole Community, or Body of men, be made the very Buttocks of the Nation, to be kick,, laſh'd, and ſlander'd, for the Crimes of Particulars; For that certainly is as remote from Reaſon, Equity, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as it would be, To Piſtol a man, becauſe his Noſe ſtands awry, or knock his Brains our, becauſe he Squints; Or indeed, becauſe the Serpent ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Eve,</hi> and ſhe <hi>Adam;</hi> whoſe Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Guilt corrupted, and deprav'd their whole Progeny. By the very ſame Crooked Rule, the Apoſtles themſelves might be call'd Traytors, becauſe <hi>Judas</hi> betray'd his Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <p>Nor can, or ſhall I ever believe it, either Pious, or Politick, to uſe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Force, but that of Arguments; for the Conviction, and Reduction of Diſputers. One may as well try to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42188:31"/>tame a Tyger with Rational Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as by Threats, or Violence; (for a man may be ſooner frighted out of his Wits, than his Opinion); to conquer long-ſetled Judgments and therefore, as the beſt <hi>Phyſick,</hi> to cure a <hi>Quartane,</hi> is, To be kind to it; So if Rational Diſcourſe, &amp; gentle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, cannot operate upon the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, &amp; mind of man, rougher Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (for what's Reaſon to one, may be Non-Senſe to another) ſhall never work a free, or plenary aſſent; for thoſe that are perforce Proſelyted, may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Diſſembling Hypocrites, but never Real-Converts. What Wiſe, or Worthy Spirits therefore would proceed ſo Irrationally, ſo Ignobly? or what advantagious Acquiſition, or Glory can there be in ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt? But this is a point, already moſt amply diſcuſs'd, by much abler penns; [Reply to the Anſwer of the <hi>Catholick-Apology;</hi> and Advocate of <hi>Conſcience-Liberty</hi>]: To them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I refer the <hi>Reader,</hi> and Ile re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Author.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who maintains conſtantly, that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42188:32"/>ſole Reaſon, in all Streights, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igences muſt Guide, and Steer us in our Courſe to our Haven, Heaven: For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>when I ask, Why you believe any Myſtery of Faith, You will anſwer perhaps, Becauſe the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church Commands you. If I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed and ask, Why do you believe, what the Preſent Church Commands you? You will ſay, Becauſe the Former Church Teaches the ſame: Why do you believe the Former Church? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi> GOD <hi>Commands you ſo to do; Why do you believe, that</hi> God <hi>Commands it? Becauſe you find it in the Scripture; Why do you believe the Scriptures to be the Word of</hi> GOD? <hi>Becauſe they were confirm'd by Miracles; Why do Miracles confirm that? Becauſe they are Workes which can proceed from nothing, but the Abſolute, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Power, of the Deity: Why ſo? Becauſe nothing contrary to, or above the Courſe of Nature can be done by Natural Agents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why ſhould I, or any man elſe, ſay any thing againſt all this? Since he has ſo pertinently, and ſolidly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42188:32"/>all the Why's himſelf: but I ſuppoſe he imagin'd, that, Syllogiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſounding the depth of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick method, or rule of Faith with this chain of Queſtions, and finding Reaſon at the bottom of it (which me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks ſhould make him the ſooner embrace it) therefore he had invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly fortifi'd his own arguments for an abſolute and independent guidance of private reaſon in all contingencies: but alas, 'tis triumphing before the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe as inconſequent, as if one ſhould ſay, my Rulers are no more than rational men, and I being a man of reaſon too, therefore my obligation ceaſeth to be rul'd by them, neither ought any man in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to command, or obey others; but is not this <hi>cum ratione inſanire?</hi> A Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which (if prevalent) would in a ſhort time deſtroy not only Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical, but all ſecular Oeconomy, and Jurisdictions! and, in the end, leave nothing but outward ſhape to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh Men from Beaſts, which have no other Superiority, or Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip amongſt them but what they get
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42188:33"/>
               <hi>Vi &amp; Armis,</hi> with their Horns and Heels. Certainly, this is very prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious (I had almoſt ſaid monſtrous) Reaſon; and ſo truly, I think, is the greateſt part of his diſcourſe, which in effect teaches, that, Divinity cannot ſtand unleſs Philoſophy ſupport it; nor St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> inſtruct, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> comment; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently no man can be a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that is not a good Philoſopher, which certainly is a very falſe and Anti-Chriſtian aſſertion.</p>
            <p>Authority and Obedience are Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relatives; there muſt be both or neither, and therefore his myſterious diſcourſe of Obedience in Spirituals (which he calls <hi>the moſt pleaſing ſmell in the Sacrifice</hi>) I ſhall never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand which totally invalidates all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Regiment and Power.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (who, I preſume, wanted not for Humane Reaſon) ſaid peremptorily, <hi>Ego verò Evangelio non crederem, niſi me Eccleſiae Catholicae commoveret Authoritas.</hi> And to the ſame Authority (leaving the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks to their Identities, Idities, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:42188:33"/>Quiddities) will I ever ſubmit both my underſtanding, &amp; my reaſon; for, would it not be very pleaſant to hear a man Catechiſe or Preach to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? and a pretty riddle for Maſter, Schollar, Preacher, and Auditour to be all in the ſame man? who, without ſome external conveyance, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward aid can no more properly or ſafely indoctrinate himſelf, than he can poſſibly put his mouth to his own ear and whiſper in it. Witty men (no doubt) may frame arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt natural and experimental De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations; as for example, Oral Loquution, or Local Motion: but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly none (though few perhaps can ſolve every particular objection) will be perſwaded, that we can neither ſpeak nor move: The ſame I ſay as to the Church; when men are (as certainly they may be) indiſputably ſatisfi'd that it is (and muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be) infallible in its Conciliar-De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions; whatſoever riſeth in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they conſequently know (though perhaps not preciſely How) muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be inconcluſive, fictitious,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42188:34"/>and falſe, without deſcending to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular diſputes, which is not only a toilſome but endleſs labour. For I have often thought, that ſince our Revolt from <hi>Rome</hi> there have been written <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi>-books enough (I ſhould not exceed, if I ſaid) to fill ten Vaticans, and yet we are in the ſame, or a worſe condition; the reaſon is, becauſe Corroſives are apply'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Lenitives, Vinegar inſtead of Oyle; wherefore I compare Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie to Phyſick, which as it cures many that would have dy'd, ſo it kills more that would have recover'd and liv'd without it.</p>
            <p>Whether what I have hitherto ſaid will have the good or ill fortune to be thought Reaſon, or not, I am not Prophet enough to know, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd enough to care, the principal motive being to employ ſome ſpare hours; but if it be eſteem'd wholly inſignificant (<hi>Solamen miſeris,</hi> &amp;c.) I am not the firſt by forty, who have written to no purpoſe; yet this I'le boldly ſay is to ſome, whatever ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments or engins of Wit are inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:42188:34"/>and directed to undermine and ſubvert the Power and Authority of God's Church will but deceive, and at laſt recoile and ruine the Inventor: And all theſe glittering words and gilded reaſons (which I confeſs are dreſt in graceful language) this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor has rally'd together againſt it, can be at moſt but Veriſimilities; they may poſſibly delight ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muze and puzle others, but ſolidly and indubitably can inform none; for I ſhould take it very kindly from him, or any man elſe, that would tell me (candidly) what thoſe imperative words (<hi>Feed my Sheep, feed my Lambs,</hi> ſpoken to St. <hi>Peter</hi>) ſignifie? if not, that there ſhould conſtantly be in God's Church (which is eſſentially compos'd of <hi>Docentes &amp; diſcentes</hi>) Paſtors, <hi>i e.</hi> Inſtructors and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, of others: For Chriſt our Lord (who never made, or ſaid any thing in vain) did not ſpeak plurally (as this Author interprets) <hi>Feed ye my Sheep, feed ye my Lambs, even where your ſelves like beſt;</hi> but, Paſce oves meas, <hi>&amp;c. Feed thou my Sheep,</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42188:35"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if all Men and Women (as this Author adviſes) ſhould turn Sheepheards and Sheepheardeſſes, (and ſo become Paſtors without Sheep, and Sheep without Paſtors, both and neither, or ſomthing and nothing, ſtraggling and feeding upon various tabifick paſtures,) who ſhould, or could feed and keep the whole Flock in order? when there would be no ſuch thing as a Flock to be kept, if all Men, Women, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of all degrees and qualities were intended by our Bleſſed Saviour to feed (<hi>i. e,</hi> to Inſtruct and Teach) themſelves; and therefore if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors doctrine (as to this particular) be reaſon, 'tis of that new ſort of reaſons, which for a while may taſt ſweetly and deliciouſly to licoriſh and licentious Palates, but in the end (I fear) they'l find 'twas but a bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweet, a pleaſant Poyſon.</p>
            <p>In a word, if his diſcourſe (as it hath plauſibility) had weight enough to make any deep impreſſion in the minds of Men (though truly I do not think this was the Author's drift)
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42188:35"/>it would neceſſarily by degrees intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Anarchy and Confuſion: for it evidently invades and diſannuls all Eccleſiaſtical Rule and Power; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilates the Paſtoral Office, and makes all Clergy-Men totally Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and Superfluous; and how can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Arguments (let them be never ſo Learnedly and Rhetorically adorn'd) have any real or intrinſecal good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or ſolidity in them, which draw ſuch mis-ſhapen, and ill favour'd Conſequences after them? <hi>Per ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum Cauſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, I compare his Treatiſe to a painted Feaſt, (for <hi>Non ſunt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, quae videntur</hi>) which may whet and encreaſe mens Appetites, but can never ſatisfie, their hunger; or rather to a Poſie of Nettles and Roſes, whereof a man cannot ſmell the ſweet, without ſtinging his Noſe; for although it be intermixt with a great deal of Scholarſhip and Wit, and carrys Reaſon in the Front, yet (according to my ſentiment) 'tis ſo Aenigmatically (if not Implouſly rapt up, that, notwithſtanding it be
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42188:36"/>but a very ſmall Volum, I cannot but think, There's a great deal too much of it; and leſt the Reader (if it have any) ſhould think ſo of mine, it ſhall not be long before I make an end.</p>
            <p>Two paſſages upon a Review of his Treatiſe I thought convenient here to inſert and ſpeak to.</p>
            <p>Firſt: Where he ſays, <hi>That ever ſince the beginning of the Chriſtian Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, there has been the Authority of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove an hundred to one againſt it, and this Authority backt and ſtrengthned with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal agreement of more than three thouſand years before it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This hundred to one, and theſe three thouſand years, makes a very great noiſe indeed, but to as little purpoſe. For, what rational man knows not, that not the greatneſs of the number (for ſo every Rebellion and Uſurpation might be juſtifi'd) but the legality of the Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of men is that which juſtly exacts and requires (and to which we are
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42188:36"/>in duty oblig'd to pay) our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and obedience.</p>
            <p>Secondly: <hi>Where he acknowledges that the beſt and trueſt</hi> Humane Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>could not have found out of it ſelf that Myſtery (by which, I ſuppoſe, he means the Incarnation) of Jeſus Chriſt, but it was neceſſary firſt to be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and as ſoon as the Spirit had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed it (which it did by Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>even</hi> Humane Reaſon <hi>was alſo to behold, and to confeſs it: not that Grace had alter'd the eye-ſight of</hi> Human-Reaſon, <hi>but drawn the object nearer to it; and till the object was brought ſo nigh, the Wiſdom of man did as ſafely not diſcern it, as it does not now the new ſtate of things which ſhall be revealed at the ſecond Coming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what news is there in all this? or who-ever queſtion'd the truth of it? but yet if that not-diſcerning, or non-credence had been accompany'd with an obſtinate reſolution to disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve or reject every thing but what
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:42188:37"/>Reaſon happen'd to find out by its own ſelf-ſearch (which would have been like a Man's denying to ſee a thing, though brought and ſet juſt before his eyes, becauſe he did not firſt ſeek and ſpy it out himſelf); that <hi>neſcience</hi> or non-diſcerning (I ſay) would not then have been ſafe, but highly cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, becauſe the things, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men might have been innocently ignorant of, after ſufficient and due propoſal, become (at leaſt <hi>neceſſitate Praecepti</hi>) <hi>neceſſariè Credenda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More than this, I know nothing he has material to be anſwer'd to.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe enſuing Verſes (which have long lain dormant) I thought not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther improper to make the Epilogue of this little work.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:42188:37"/>
            <head>Upon his Majeſty's Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Condeſcention, to a Toleration in —72. A year which I could wiſh had always laſted.</head>
            <q>
               <l>— Regum eſt.</l>
               <l>Parcere ſubjectis &amp; debellare ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbos.</l>
            </q>
            <l>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Royal Pilot (ſtudying how to Steer,</l>
            <l>And pleaſe each individual Paſſenger,</l>
            <l>Embarqu'd with him) finds no Rocks nor Shelvs</l>
            <l>So formidable to us as our Selves.</l>
            <l>For our inteſtine Feuds and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</l>
            <l>Endanger moſt the Ship of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</l>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:42188:38"/>
            <l>And what's the Source, from whence this miſchief flows,</l>
            <l>And in its progreſs ſo deformed grows?</l>
            <l>But at the Tinder-boxes of our brains,</l>
            <l>Striking new lights, and for our fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick pains</l>
            <l>Groaping in darkneſs, this (unhappy Fate!)</l>
            <l>Breeds a Confuſion both in Church and State.</l>
            <l>But as the great King, with a Fiat ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e</l>
            <l>Light out of darkneſs, and his breath convey'd</l>
            <l>Form to the Chaos; ſo, by this Act of Grace,</l>
            <l>Ours, blows foul weather from the cloudy face</l>
            <l>Of his <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> timely to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</l>
            <l>State-pleuriſies, which no medicament</l>
            <l>Can cure, but letting Blood, and now we ſee</l>
            <l>
               <hi>England</hi> a Free-State, and a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy;</l>
            <l>And may't unanimouſly be confeſt,</l>
            <l>The Publick Good's our private Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt;</l>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:42188:38"/>
            <l>That (not Religion) we ſhall find to be</l>
            <l>The ſtrongeſt Bond of our Fidelity.</l>
            <l>But thoſe that would (like <hi>Eſops</hi> Dog) have all,</l>
            <l>Catching at ſhadows, let the ſubſtance fall.</l>
            <l>Theſe Peccant humours our Phyſitian ſtrives</l>
            <l>T'aſſwage with ſoft and gentle Leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives;</l>
            <l>In which Attempt, whether his Wiſdom, or</l>
            <l>His Clemency exceeds, is dubious, for</l>
            <l>The Monſter-multitude (like flouds confin'd)</l>
            <l>By perſecution grow the more combin'd,</l>
            <l>And forcing Vent, or Iſſues (like the Sea</l>
            <l>Rage but with more impetuoſity.</l>
            <l>But theſe Religious Struglings finding ſcope,</l>
            <l>By this Indulgence of our Engliſh Pope,</l>
            <l>Thoſe rapid Zealots may (this being done)</l>
            <l>Recurr, and in the proper Channel run.</l>
            <l>But if this fails, as in the Stars we ſee</l>
            <l>A Regular Irregularity;</l>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:42188:39"/>
            <l>So in our Engliſh Sphear (I hope) 'till prove</l>
            <l>Theſe various Sects may without claſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing move;</l>
            <l>And not Create their own Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes ſtill.</l>
            <l>In ſhort, we may be happy if we will.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:42188:39"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. <hi>line</hi> 18. <hi>oppoſed,</hi> read <hi>oppoſite.</hi> p. 12. l. 22. <hi>corporal,</hi> r. <hi>corporeal.</hi> p. 33. l. 12 after <hi>one,</hi> r. <hi>true.</hi> p. 34 l. 2. <hi>Canary, Claret, Syder, and Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadine, are,</hi> r. <hi>Canary, Claret, and Syder Muſcadine</hi> p. 39. l. 24. <hi>in ſo,</hi> r. <hi>in ſe.</hi> p. 51. l. 2. <hi>by,</hi> r. <hi>to.</hi> p. 51 l. 23. after <hi>Prophecyes,</hi> add, <hi>and.</hi> p. 52. l. 10. <hi>by,</hi> r. <hi>to.</hi> p. 53. l. 7. after <hi>ſtretch,</hi> add, <hi>it.</hi> p. 55. l. 1. <hi>his</hi> r. <hi>the.</hi> p. 55. l. 3. after <hi>Election,</hi> dele, <hi>or choice.</hi> p. 55. l. 24. after <hi>Pitch,</hi> add, <hi>and.</hi> p. 58. l. 28. <hi>Dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> r. <hi>Diſſenters.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
